Guide to the A. J. Antoon papers, 1961-1991
The New York Public Library. Billy Rose Theatre Division.
A. J. Antoon papers
1961-1991
*T-Mss 1992-040
21347
Antoon, A. J. (Alfred Joseph), 1944-1992
The New York Public Library. Billy Rose Theatre Division. New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, Dorothy and Lewis B. Cullman Center 40 Lincoln Center Plaza, New York, NY 10023-7498
24 boxes (11 lin. ft.
The papers of A. J. Antoon contain scripts, photographs, correspondence, writings, contracts and financial papers. Annotated scripts and items from productions Antoon directed make up the bulk of the collection. The collection also contains written works by Antoon including two screenplays.
Alfred Joseph Antoon, Jr. (1944-1992) was an award-winning stage director who, at the young age of twenty-seven, was nominated for a Tony Award for two plays in the same year.
A.J. (as he liked to be called) was born December 7, 1944 in Methuen, Massachusetts and became active in the theater arts in high school. After high school, Antoon studied for the priesthood at Shadowbrook Jesuit Seminary in Lenox, Massachusetts and also became a student at Boston College. He earned his bachelor's degree from Boston College in 1968. Antoon was accepted to the Yale School of Drama but left after one-and-a-half years to work in New York.
Antoon's professional directing career began in 1971 with Story Theatre, adaptations of Chekhov and Tolstoy at St. Clement's Church Theatre in New York. That same year he began his association with Joseph Papp and the New York Shakespeare Festival (NYSF). Antoon had presented an original play written by Yale friend Robert Montgomery to Papp while at Yale. Papp liked it and offered A.J. the director's job. Subject to Fits opened February 14, 1971 at the Public Theater and became a hit. It later moved to London and was staged by the Royal Shakespeare Company. Before 1971 was over, Antoon also had directing success with the NYSF production of Shakespeare's Cymbeline.
The year 1973 was Antoon's most award-winning as a director. In that year he was nominated for a Tony Award for both Much Ado About Nothing and That Championship Season. He won the Tony for That Championship Season, and was also given the Drama Desk Award and the Drama Critics Circle Award. Much Ado About Nothing was later adapted for television and ran on CBS as a three-hour special. To cap the year, Antoon received an Honorary Doctorate from his alma mater Boston College.
Antoon went on to direct seventeen major plays and musicals, seven of which were Broadway productions. The following are highlights of his professional career that spanned twenty years:
1971 Cymbeline with Christopher Walken and William Devane.
1971 Subject to Fits with Jason Miller.
1972 Much Ado About Nothing with Sam Waterston and Barnard Hughes.
1972 That Championship Season with Charles Durning and Paul Sorvino.
1973 The Good Doctor with Christopher Plummer and Marsha Mason.
1974 The Dance of Death with Robert Shaw and Zoe Caldwell.
1975 Trelawany of the 'Wells' with Broadway debuts of Meryl Streep and Mandy Patinkin.
1977 The Effect of Gamma Rays... with Shelly Winters and Carol Kane.
1979 Nasty Rumors and Final Remarks with Gail Strickland. Antoon won the Villager Award.
1979 The Art of Dining with Dianne Wiest. Antoon won an Obie Award in 1980.
1984 The Rink with Chita Rivera and Liza Minelli. Antoon received a Drama Desk nomination.
1986 South Pacific with Richard Kiley, performed in Los Angeles.
1987 -Sherlock's Last Case with Frank Langella
1988 A Midsummer Night's Dream with F. Murray Abraham and Elizabeth McGovern.
1990 Taming of the Shrew with Morgan Freeman and Tracey Ullman.
1991 Song of Singapore his last show.
The A.J. Antoon Papers were donated to the Billy Rose Theatre Division in March 1992 with additional installments received in June and October (one notebook was added in June 1996). The collection was conserved, rehoused, and reprocessed in 1995. Clippings were photocopied for conservation purposes.
The A.J. Antoon Papers cover the years 1961 to 1991 and contain general and personal correspondence, financial papers, calendars, writings, scripts, photographs, and clippings. The bulk of this collection lies in the Professional Productions series which includes nine boxes (7-15). Most of the items contained in this series are scripts with Antoon's notations, production notes and set design drawings, cast contact sheets, agency correspondence, and contracts and legal agreements.
Antoon was not only a gifted director but a writer as well. There are five boxes of Antoon's writings, box 17 includes writings from Shadowbrook Seminary and Boston College. Boxes 18-21 contain the screenplays of Snow White and Hotheads and the script from his musical version of Treasure Island. Box 22 contains treatments and ideas for proposed productions, most of which were Antoon's original concepts.
Although A.J. Antoon focused his talents on the theater, it must be noted that he did direct the television production of Much Ado About Nothing and a television pilot film for Norman Lear entitled Hereafter. However, this collection does not contain any items from those efforts.
The papers of A.J. Antoon are arranged in ten series and two sub-series. They include:
I. Correspondence [1961-1991]
II. Personal Papers [1965-1989]
III. Financial Papers [1972-1990]
IV.Amateur Productions [1961-1968]
V. Professional Productions [1971-1991]
VI. Production Clippings [1971-1990]
VII. Writings [1962-1985]
Sub-series 1-Writings-Amateur [ca. 1962-1969]
Sub-series 2-Writings-Professional [1975-1985]
VIII. Proposed Productions [197?-1985]
XI. Miscellaneous Scripts [ca.1972-1986]
X. Original Art Work [1972-1986]
Gift, Perez, Peter, 04/03/1992
Audiovisual materials separated from archival collections are cataloged individually and can be found in the Library catalog. Search CATNYP, The New York Public Library catalog.
PHOTOGRAPHS
The following photographs have been separated from the A.J. Antoon Papers and added to the photograph file:
Cymbeline-2 (B file)
Genesis-10 (B file)
The Good Doctor-1 (A file)
King of Hearts-7 (B file)
A Midsummer Night's Dream-15 (B file)
The Rink-2 (B file)
Subject to Fits-2 (B file)
That Championship Season-3 (B file)
PROGRAMS
The following programs from these productions have been separated from the A.J. Antoon Papers:
The Art of Dining
Derelict
Genesis
King of Hearts (signed by Antoon)
Obie Awards, 25th Anniversary (1980)
The Rink
That Championship Season (signed by Antoon and actor Paul Sorvino)
Trelawny of the 'Wells'
POSTERS
The following window cards and posters have been separated from the A.J. Antoon Papers:
The Art of Dining-14" x 22" window card
Dance of Death-14" x 12" window card
The Effect of Gamma Rays...-14" x 22" window card
Genesis-22" x 29" poster
The Good Doctor-14" x 22" window card
Much Ado About Nothing-65" x 40" poster
The Palace of Amateurs-11" x 17" window card
The Rink-14" x 22" window card
Shakespeare in the Park-30" x 46" poster
South Pacific-14" x 22" window card signed by cast
Subject to Fits-13" x 21" window card
That Championship Season-14" x 22" window card
Trelawny of the 'Wells'-14" x 22" window card
*T-Cabinet
A framed and signed photograph of the male cast members from The Rink was sent to the T-Cabinet.
Videotapes
Video tapes sent to Theatre on Film and Tape Archive (TOFT):
The Rink (excerpt)-Videotaped by ABC Television, Eyewitness News, used by critic Joel Siegel. 3/4" tape, 28 minutes, TOFT # NCOX 685.Song of Singapore-Videotape of performance. VHS SP color, 112 minutes, TOFT # NCOV 1111.
Be My Guest-Antoon interviewed by Michall Jeffers for Continental Cablevision, 1989. 3/4" tape, 20 minutes, TOFT # NCOX 545.
Audiotapes
Audiotapes separated to the Rodgers and Hammerstein Archives of Recorded Sound:
Genesis-6 audio cassettes, 2-12 inch reel-to-reel tapes of live performance
A.J. Antoon papers, video and sound recordings
Collection is open to the public. Library policy on photography and photocopying will apply. Advance notice may be required.
Photocopying prohibited.
Antoon, A. J. (Alfred Joseph), 1944-1992; Howe, Tina; Kander, John; Miller, Jason; Papp, Joseph; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616; Sills, Paul; Sills, Paul, 1927-2008; Simon, Neil; New York Shakespeare Festival; Musical theater -- United States; Theater -- Production and direction; Theater -- United States -- 20th century; Scripts; Theatrical producers and directors
- Series I: Correspondence, 1961-1991; 920875; Arranged by type of correspondence.
  The series contains correspondence written to and by Antoon. Much of it is personal correspondence from his Jesuit and Boston College friend Paul Swift(a.k.a. Porky). There are application letters to colleges from Antoon requesting admission into drama schools. Also a number of letters from Antoon's two legal representatives, Richard Rosenthal and Franklin Weissberg, concerning financial issues, agency matters, and contracts.
  1 box (.4 lin. ft.)
  - Correspondence - Arrupe, Peter, S.J.,., 1967; 920876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Miguel Chivite, 1976; 920877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Robert Lantz, 1981; 920878 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Peter Link, 1977; 920879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Betty McGonagle, 1969; 920880 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Charlie O'Leary, 1977; 920881 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Joseph Papp, 1971; 920882 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Anthony Scully, 1967; 920883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Paul Swift, 1972; 920884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poetry and writings - Paul Swift, 920885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs - Paul Swift, 920886 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Scripts - Paul Swift, 920887 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Fred Tollini, 1979; 920888 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1968, 920889 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - John Collins, 1969; 920890 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Stan Edelman, 1980; 920891 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - Society of Jesus, 1967; 920892 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Yale University School of Drama, 1968; 920893 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General correspondence, 1961; 920894 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General correspondence, 1975; 920895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General correspondence--Agency/legal, 1977; 920896 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1965-1989; 920897; 2 boxes (.6 lin. ft.
  A bulk of the items [1965-1968] are papers written by Antoon while at Boston College. It also includes personal photographs, resumes, and a thank you note from director Mike Nichols. Box 2 contains personal calendars for years 1979 (Jan., Feb., March, April), 1981, 1982, 1984, 1985, and 1986.
  Arranged by form of material.
  - Boston College term papers, 1965; 920898 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Boston College term papers, 1966; 920899 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Boston College term papers, 1968; 920900 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Boston College writings, 1965; 920901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings / Mike Nichols, 1966; 920902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Last will and testament, 1976; 920903 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cards and invitations, 920904 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Personal photographs and slides, 920905 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personal ephemera, 920906 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Resumes / A.J. Antoon, 920907 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Appointment books and calendars, 1979; 920908 (Box 3)
- Series III: Financial Papers, 1972-1990; 920909; 2 boxes (.8 lin. ft.
  This series contains income tax returns and financial statements from both personal accounts and his corporate accounts under Dogberry Enterprises.
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Personal income tax returns, 1972; 920910 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Personal income tax returns, 1980; 920911 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Personal income tax returns, 1984; 920912 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial statements, 1984; 920913 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial statements, 1985; 920914 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Financial statements, 1986; 920915 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Financial statements, 1987; 920916 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wyckford partnership correspondence, 1980; 920917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Apartment lease and correspondence, 1978; 920918 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Income tax and analysis / Dogberry Enterprises, 1978; 920919 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Income tax and analysis / Dogberry Enterprises, 1981; 920920 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Income tax and analysis / Dogberry Enterprises, 1984; 920921 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Income tax and analysis / Dogberry Enterprises, 1986; 920922 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reconciliation of accounts / Dogberry Enterprises, 1983; 920923 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reconciliation of accounts / Dogberry Enterprises, 1985; 920924 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Statements of assets and liabilities / Dogberry Enterprises, 1983; 920925 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Statements of assets and liabilities / Dogberry Enterprises, 1985; 920926 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Defined benefit pension plan and trust / Dogberry Enterprises, 1984; 920927 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Report on actuarial valuation of pension / Dogberry Enterprises, 1984; 920928 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Liquid assets / Dogberry Enterprises, 1987; 920929 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Amateur Productions, 1961-1968; 920930; 1 box (.2 lin. ft.
  Included in this series are adaptations from Shakespeare and the Bible written and usually directed and performed by Antoon. High school productions were staged from 1961-1962 (includes clippings and photographs); Shadowbrook Jesuit Seminary productions from 1963-1965, and Boston College productions from 1966-1968. Boston College productions contain the script and photographs from Antoon's performance of his original work There the Antic Sits. Also included are clippings from the Tufts' production of Jean Anouilh's The Cavern. Antoon was a member of the Tufts University Summer Acting Company in 1967 and played the part of the Seminarist.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Theatrical performances / Central Catholic High School (Lawrence, Mass.), 1961; 920931 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and photographs / A.J. Antoon, 1961; 920932 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Daniel / A.J. Antoon, 1963; 920933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The hollow crown / A.J. Antoon, 1963; 920934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The chosen ones / A.J. Antoon, 1964; 920935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Job / A.J. Antoon, 1965; 920936 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - There the antic sits / A.J. Antoon, 1966; 920937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - There the antic sits / A.J. Antoon, 1966; 920938 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Medieval mystery plays / A.J. Antoon, 1967; 920939 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Clippings / A.J. Antoon, 1967; 920940 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Erasmus notes / A.J. Antoon, 1968; 920941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series V: Professional Productions, 1971-1991; 920942; 9 boxes (3.4 lin. ft.
  The Art of Dining[1978-1979] Written by Tina Howe, this Joseph Papp production opened at the Public Theater, December 6, 1979, ran three days, then moved to the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, D.C. for five weeks. It then returned to the Public Theater in New York. The show starred Dianne Wiest and Kathy Bates. Antoon won an Obie Award for best direction in 1980. Includes director's script, agency/legal correspondence with Antoon's contract, and program covers.
  The Dance of Death [1974] Written by August Strindberg and adapted by A.J. Antoon. This was another Joseph Papp production, running for two weeks at the Annenberg Center, University of Pennsylvania, in early March. It then moved to New York and began previews at the Vivian Beaumont Theater on March 21. Opening night was April 5, 1974, with the show running through May 5. Robert Shaw and Zoe Caldwell starred. Includes director's script and a Minnesota Theatre Company program from 1966 where the play was also performed.
  Derelict,[1981-1982] By Robert Schenkkan, the play had its world premiere at the Studio Arena Theatre, Buffalo, NY on February 12, 1982 and ran through March 7. Director's script and cast contact sheet are included.
  Double Cross,[1988-1991] By Gary Bohlke, it had its World Premiere at the Pasadena Playhouse, January 11, 1991. Included are edited scripts from 1990, scene breakdowns, sound plot, and prop list.
  The Effect of Gamma Rays...,[1977-1978] Written by Paul Zindel, this production opened March 14, 1978 at the Biltmore Theatre, NY and starred Shelly Winters and Carol Kane. The two-act drama closed after sixteen performances. The file contains director's script and contact sheet plus agency/legal correspondence from 1978 regarding a royalty dispute.
  Genesis, [1985-1989] This was a concept many years in the making in Antoon's mind and became a full-length production in 1988. The music is by Michael Ward with book and lyrics written by Antoon and Robert Montgomery who also wrote Subject to Fits. A NYSF production, performed at the Public Theater/LuEsther Hall, it opened November 29 and ran through January 22, 1989. It was also staged at the University of South Carolina's Longstreet Theatre, April 6, 7, 8, 1990. Collection contains two scripts, a rewrite from 1988, collaboration agreements (1988-1989), correspondence (1985, 1988-1989) which includes form pitch letters sent to producers/theaters asking for support, and photographs and slides from performances.
  The Girl I Left Behind Me,[1981] Written by David Belasco in 1893, Antoon directed three performances near the end of 1981 at Middlebury College's Wright Theatre. Antoon was also visiting professor of theater at this Vermont college during winter term. Contains director's script, production notes, sound cues, a farewell card signed by cast members, and correspondence to and from Middlebury College.
  The Good Doctor, [1973-1980] Written by Neil Simon, adapted from stories by Anton Chekov. First ran at the Shubert Theatre from November 1, 1973 through the 10th. It then opened at the Eugene O'Neill Theatre November 27, 1973, and starred Christopher Plummer, Barnard Hughes, and Marsha Mason. The show closed on May 26, 1974 after 208 regular performances. Included in the collection is Simon's first draft from 1973, Antoon's script, stage drawings, agency/legal correspondence with Antoon's contract.
  A Good Life,[1986] A musical for children by Stanley Silverman (book and lyrics by Jeff Moss), adapted from a Russian folk tale, it opened April 18, 1986 and ran for one week at the Kennedy Center Theater Lab, Washington, D.C. Includes script, stage drawings, production notes, reviews, and copy of The Soldier and Death, the original story from which this musical is based.
  House of Blue Leaves,[1981] This play by John Guare was performed at the Berkshire Theatre Festival in Stockbridge, Massachusetts and ran from July 7, to July 22, 1981. File only contains Antoon's contract.
  King of Hearts, [1977] The musical by Peter Link (lyrics by Jacob Brackman, book by Steve Tesich) was based on the screenplay by Philippe de Broca and Daniel Boulanger. The show opened at the Westport Country Playhouse, Connecticut on August 30, 1977 and ran through September 10. Young Robby Benson was the featured star. Producer Joe Kipness replaced some of the original creative staff including Antoon before moving it to Broadway. Box contains the final script, first and second drafts, annotated drafts, lyrics, production notes, cast list, and photographs of costume drawings. There is also a transcript of a discussion between Antoon, Peter Link, and choreographer Ron Field about the production. Ron Field later directed the show on Broadway.
  A Life in the Theatre,[1987] The play by David Mamet starred Alec Baldwin and ran January 17 through January 30, 1987 at the Palace Theater of Arts, Stamford, Connecticut. Director's script included.
  A Midsummer Night's Dream,[1988] This Shakespeare play was a NYSF production set in turn-of-the-century Brazil and starred F. Murray Abraham and Elizabeth McGovern. Performances ran from January 12 to January 24,1988 at the New York Shakespeare Festival's Anspacher Theater. File contains production notes, casting list of minor characters, and photocopies of costume drawings.
  Much Ado About Nothing, [1972-1973] This was one of the first plays directed by Antoon for Joseph Papp and the New York Shakespeare Festival and was one of his most successful. The two-act comedy opened August 16, 1972 in Central Park's Delacorte Theater and ran for twenty performances. The production was moved to Broadway's Winter Garden on November 11, 1972 and ran through February 11, 1973. It was then produced as a three-hour television special for CBS and aired February 2, 1973. All three productions earned praise for the 28-year-old Antoon plus a Tony nomination. Sam Waterston and Barnard Hughes starred. Contains set and prop list, a parody written by Samuel Satin sent to Joseph Papp, and color snap-shots of Sam Waterston and Kathleen Widdoes outdoors at the Delacorte Theater.
  Nasty Rumors and Final Remarks, [1979] Written by Susan Miller, this was another NYSF production that opened at the Public Theater on April 12, 1979 and ran for twelve performances. Antoon was given the Villager Award for excellence in directing. Includes director's script, contact sheet, and Villager Award.
  The Palace of Amateurs,[1982] A play by John Faro PiRoman had its world premiere on August 18, 1982 at the Berkshire Theatre Festival, Stockbridge, Massachusetts. The show ran through August 28. File includes script and screenplay, casting call list, contact sheet, photocopies of checks sent to Antoon for director's fees.
  The Rink,[1982-1984] This musical written by John Kander, with lyrics by Fred Ebb, book by Terrence McNally, was a major Broadway production directed by Antoon. It opened February 9, 1984 at the Martin Beck Theater and ran for 129 performances. The show starred Liza Minnelli and Chita Rivera and earned Antoon a Drama Desk Award nomination. Box 12 contains the final script and revisions. Box 13 contains cast contact and audition sheets, production and rewrite notes, agreements and contracts, photocopies of royalty checks and box office statements, a laminated flyer, and the Drama Desk Award nomination.
  Sherlock's Last Case,[1987] A New York Shakespeare Festival production, written by Charles Marowitz, it starred Frank Langella as Sherlock Holmes. The show opened at the Eisenhower Theater in Washington, D.C. and ran from July 1 to August 1, 1987. It then moved to the Nederlander Theater in New York, and opened August 20, 1987. After 124 performances, it closed December 6. Includes director's script, and correspondence concerning Antoon's royalty dispute.
  Song of Singapore,[1991] A musical by Erik Frandsen, et al., and book by Allen Katz, this was the last show directed by Antoon. The show began preview performances on May 7, 1991 at the Irving Place theater, opening night was May 31. Folder contains director's script.
  South Pacific,[1984-1986] This Rogers and Hammerstein revival opened in Los Angeles at the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, May 14, 1986 and featured Richard Kiley. Performances ran through July 6. Included in the collection are ten color photocopies of the set designs, thirty 4x7 photographs from the performance, scripts, audition notes and a letter from William Hammerstein providing his thoughts on the production.
  Story Theater,[1971]Story Theater was the start of Antoon's professional career. These adaptations of Tolstoy and Chekov stories began at Yale with author Paul Sills. Performances where held in early 1971 at the St. Clement's Church Theatre in New York. Folder contains a notebook of telephone numbers, production notes, cast lists, and drawings.